<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><rss xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:openSearch='http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearchrss/1.0/' version='2.0'><channel><atom:id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592</atom:id><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2008 07:21:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><title>Sri Chinmoy Inspiration</title><description></description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/spirit.html</link><managingEditor>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</managingEditor><generator>Blogger</generator><openSearch:totalResults>25</openSearch:totalResults><openSearch:startIndex>1</openSearch:startIndex><openSearch:itemsPerPage>25</openSearch:itemsPerPage><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7188101454324467155</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2007 12:23:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-10-05T08:29:15.408-07:00</atom:updated><title>New Blog</title><description>Sri Chinmoy Inspiration has moved to a new wordpress Blog:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;Please visit our &lt;a style="font-weight: bold;" href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog"&gt;New Wordpress Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Articles from New Blog&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog/meditation/how-to-gain-control-of-your-own-thoughts/"&gt;How To Control your thoughts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog/life/finding-time-for-relaxation/"&gt;Finding Time for Relaxation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog/life/the-power-of-simplicity/"&gt;The Power of Simplicity&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/08/new-blog.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-4080220186942505612</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2007 14:42:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-08-15T08:47:38.628-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>conflict</category><title>What Creates Conflict?</title><description>From time immemorial, the world has witnessed unnecessary conflict and suffering. Why does this occur? Is conflict an inevitable part of human nature?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are many different outer reasons for conflict; but, the source of conflict always begins in the human mind. If we do not have peace of mind, conflict in the outer world is inevitable. These are often the inner reasons for outer conflict.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;1. Superiority&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is the ego that separates and divides. It is the ego that gives us feelings of inferiority and superiority. When we have feelings of superiority, we wish to assert our supremacy over others. We feel justified in seeking to change / enlighten / improve other people. It is these concepts which are often at the source of conflict. Because we feel our way of life and beliefs are better than others, we desire to convert others to our way of living. This gives us the self justification to create conflict. Closely related to feeling of supremacy are ideas of inferiority. Quite often we feel that others are seeking to prove their superiority over us. Because of this we are afraid and defensive. We have a subconscious feeling of inferiority and therefore, feel obliged to assert ourselves; conflict becomes a way of asserting and proving ourselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Separation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Another root source of conflict is the idea of separation between ourselves and other people. This can manifest in cultural / religious or national separation. It is this sense of separation that causes us to look upon the other side as our enemy. It becomes impossible to sympathise or have any feeling of oneness. Because there is a sense of separation we become indifferent to the suffering of others. If we identified with other people as an extended part of ourselves, we would emphasise with their suffering and seek to avoid it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Pride&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pride is related both to superiority and separation. It is pride that encourages us to feel separate from others. Pride means that we become unwilling to back down or admit that we were wrong. Because of pride we pursue strategies that perpetuate conflict. If we could swallow our pride we would be willing to apologise for doing the wrong thing and thus enable a resolution to conflict. Unfortunately, we give too much opinion to our ego and feelings of pride. We wrongly assume that to admit a mistake is a sign of weakness. Actually, to admit a mistake and change our course of action requires strength. If we are doing the wrong thing, continuing this course of action, only aggravates the situation and makes it worse.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;If your mind is consumed  &lt;br /&gt;With disproportionate pride,  &lt;br /&gt;How can your heart be inundated&lt;br /&gt;With oneness-delight?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/"&gt;Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. A Long Memory.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many insoluble conflicts go back a long time. Each party is able to bring a long list of grievances to any negotiating table. These grievances and perceived slights often remain a stumbling block to negotiation. Usually in response to one side's grievances, the opposite side merely respond with their own list of grievances. When people are attached to the wrongs of the past, it becomes very difficult to create a harmonious future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. Priorities.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For many people harmony is not their highest priority. Whilst this remains the case, it becomes very difficult to do anything about it. To have an end to conflict, it is necessary that people sincerely aspire for this. Quite often, it becomes more important that we are "proved right" rather than work to dissolve conflict and suffering.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Related Posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/art-of-happiness.html"&gt;The Art of Happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/what-creates-conflict.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-1918261875930147383</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2007 21:53:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-27T10:17:59.453-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>anger</category><title>Keeping your Anger under Control</title><description>Anger is like a snake in the deep grass. - Remaining hidden for most of the time, it can suddenly rise up to strike us unexpectedly. Anger, may be justified, but it rarely helps us deal with a situation. Anger also leaves us feeling depressed, unbalanced, and nursing a sense of injustice. Some people feel anger is good, because it motivates them to do something. However, anger is neither necessary nor desirable. When we look at a situation through the mists of anger, our judgment becomes clouded; we react hastily, in a way that often aggravates the situation. If we are a victim of injustice, this does not mean we should remain passive. We can act - but, in a way that will improve the situation for ourselves, not in a way that makes it worse.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;How To Control Anger&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt; 1.  Don't respond immediately. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we feel anger come upon us. Wait a moment before responding. Take a few calm deep breathes; we will find that after the initial surge, the anger subsides. After, even a moment of reflection, we realise the situation is not as grave as our mind's first reaction. It is advisable to remember the advice of Thomas Jefferson:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"When angry count to ten before you speak. If very angry, count to one hundred"&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we do respond straight away we will be liable to say something we regret later. Words spoken in anger leave a lasting remark and it can be hard to undue their effects.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Remember some good qualities of the person.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is often the case that 90% of the time we get angry with friends and families. If we live with someone, it is inevitable we will find some of their daily habits irritating. At some point we may snap and get angry with them. If this occurs try remembering 10 of their good qualities. If we can force ourselves to think of even 1, it will reduce our anger significantly. If we are honest, their good qualities are far more powerful then their bad quality of putting the cornflakes in the wrong drawer. It may sound daft, but often anger can arise from minor issues. Try to look beyond small insignificant issues to consider the bigger picture.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Forgiveness.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Other people will inevitably do bad things; this is the way of the world. However, we can be wise and try to take a more enlightened position. If we respond to their faults with anger, we will only strengthen them. If we are able to forgive them, we may actually shame them into doing the right thing. When they see our response is flooded with inner peace, they may feel embarrassed at their behaviour; in the future they may seek to avoid doing it. Forgiveness of other's defects, may not be the natural instinct of the mind. But, if we sincerely forgive them, we will help our situation. At some time, others will appreciate our compassion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Forgiveness does not mean condoning their actions. But, let us start with the minor infractions of our close ones; next time they annoy us, respond with a compassionate attitude rather than anger and see the difference.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Meditation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To permanently overcome anger we need to bring to the fore inner peace. Inner peace is the antidote to anger; it is only through inner peace that we can permanently subdue the force of anger. &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/resources/meditation.html"&gt;Real Meditation&lt;/a&gt; brings to the fore inner peace; this is because in meditation we are able to detach ourselves from our thoughts. When we learn to detach ourselves from our thoughts, we can easily detach ourselves from destructive emotions such as anger.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. See Anger as an Enemy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Remind yourself anger will make yourself miserable. Make a conscious decision not to allow anger to poison your system. Anger may come quickly, but if we ignore anger, it will soon dissipate. Value your inner peace. If we lose our inner peace we lose something most precious and valuable.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Anger says: &lt;br /&gt;"I can destroy&lt;br /&gt;The whole world."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Peace says:&lt;br /&gt;"Not when I work&lt;br /&gt;Inside you."&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;From: Sri Chinmoy Library &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/somebody-listen/17.html"&gt;"Anger Says"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://digg.com/submit?phase=2&amp;url=http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/keeping-your-anger-under-control.html&amp;title=Keeping Your Anger under Control&amp;bodytext=Tips to Control and reduce anger. &amp;topic=health"&gt;Submit To Digg&lt;/a&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/keeping-your-anger-under-control.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7278113791285276865</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2007 20:25:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-23T13:28:37.869-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spirituality</category><title>The Meaning of Freedom</title><description>&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/statues-sea-777625.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/statues-sea-777622.jpg" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Freedom:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;the ability to do as we choose; freedom from coercion and externally imposed constraints.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are many different types of freedom. Firstly, there is political freedom: the freedom to live without constraints from the government. There is also individual freedom: the ability to choose as we see fit, without constraints from others. Finally, there is spiritual freedom; this necessitates being free from the limitations and ignorance of our own human mind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are clearly different ways to use our freedom. For a drug addict, freedom involves the ability to take as many drugs as his habit forces him. However, the more drugs he takes, the more his concept of freedom is narrowed; the addiction means his life revolves around the necessity of finding and taking drugs. In one sense he has the freedom to take drugs; on the other hand by becoming an addict he loses the freedom to choose anything else. It is here that we start to question whether individual freedom is the highest kind of freedom.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The human mind is a creature of habit. When we make decisions, quite often we make them because that is what we are used to doing. We hear people say "I know I shouldn't be doing this" or "I wish I could give this up." However, if we are reluctantly drawn to do an action out of compulsion, can that be freedom? -&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is not just in the consumption of addictive drugs that human freedom proves illusory; we can also examine how the traits of the mind create limitations in everyday thought patterns. For example, the mind creates habitual responses to certain situations. If we get criticised, we feel miserable; in the face of injustice, we get angry. It is most difficult to control these emotions; they seem an inevitable part of our nature. We wish to be free, but no matter how often these experiences occur, our reaction is the same. Furthermore, these in built responses of the mind unmistakably lead to suffering and depression.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We wish to be free but at the same time we are slave to the instinctive responses of the mind. What kind of freedom is it when we are at the mercy of events in the outer world? Is it really freedom when one word of criticism, can plunge us into the depths of despair?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The highest experience of freedom can only occur when we can be detached from events in the outer world. Freedom means we need to have our own emotions and responses under our control.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"Spiritual freedom is our liberation from the mire of self-created bondage." [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Freedom means that no matter what may happen to us, we can maintain a sense of inner peace, poise and detachment. This inner peace is essential for a real sense of freedom. It is only when we have boundless inner peace that we are not a victim to our own negative thoughts and habitual responses.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;How much of our choices are conditioned by the society in which we grow up? If we are honest, we have to admit that if we were born in a different situation, a different place, our life choices would be very different. This is because our choices are a reflection of what society teaches and expects. We may feel it is our freedom to live as we do. But, in reality, this freedom is heavily influenced by sociology and our limited perspective.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;However, if we can gain an access to our soul, we develop an insight into our life's purpose. This soul's purpose is detached from social expectations. This is real freedom, because we have the ability to choose according to the aspirations of our soul. We are not just choosing what is expected of us. To be really free, we have to be able to detach ourselves from social conditioning and the ignorance of the mind. This can occur only if we dive deep within. This is the difference between inner and outer freedom&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We may have a freedom to choose anything on an outer plane; but, this freedom does not give us abiding satisfaction; why? This freedom is only a freedom to choose from a limited egoistic perspective. Real freedom is only possible when we become one with the universal consciousness. This consciousness is not constrained by the limitations of the mind. It is all expanding, infinite bliss and real freedom. It is because of this inner bliss and ecstasy that spiritual aspirants are not satisfied by the so-called freedoms of the world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;An aspiring seeker does not just want a limited outer freedom; he wishes to escape the cycle of bondage that inevitably creates suffering. In fact, the spiritual seeker, may look upon the outer freedom as a false kind of freedom; a freedom which keeps from discovering our true self.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"What is false freedom? False freedom is our constant and deliberate acceptance of ignorance and our conscious existence in ignorance. What is real freedom? Real freedom is our conscious awareness of our inner divinity, and our constant inseparable oneness with the Inner Pilot" [2]&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is for this reason that the Buddha gave up his kingdom to become a wandering ascetic. In the material world he had all he could wish for, but Siddharta knew that even with this outer freedom he was tied to the inevitable suffering, death and pain of life. The Buddha wanted freedom, he wanted to taste the bliss of nirvana and escape the endless cycle of death and rebirth. With great determination and aspiration, the Buddha transcended his sense of ego; he entered in the perfect freedom of nirvana. In this consciousness, the Buddha was free from the temptations and forces of the world; he regained his Buddha hood and understood the real nature of life, freedom and his Self.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1]  &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/sri-chinmoy-freedom-boats/part2/3.html"&gt;Freedom&lt;/a&gt; by Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[2] &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/tears-nation-hearts/7.html"&gt;Freedom:&lt;/a&gt; From the Tears of Nation hearts by Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Picture credit: by Kedar Misani, Sri Chinmoy Centre Galleries</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/meaning-of-freedom.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7096319626620350437</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2007 17:40:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-27T08:18:00.053-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>self improvement</category><title>How to Overcome Shyness</title><description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Shy:&lt;/span&gt; being reserved or having or showing nervousness or timidity in the company of other people.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Shyness is an emotion many people suffer from at some time. It creates awkwardness in social situations and can damage our job prospects. Some people may feel their shyness is incurable - "I'm just a shy person". Others may even feel there is nothing wrong with being shy, they may equate it to a type of modesty. However, we can definitely overcome shyness. It is also very much worth doing because shyness does not help us in anyway. It is not really about being modest and humble; shyness is primarily about covering up our natural state of being; if anything it is a false modesty.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Overcoming Shyness&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;1. Look upon shyness as a thing to overcome.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we consciously or subconsciously cherish our shyness, we will never be able to overcome it. We should feel that shyness prevents us from becoming the person that we really are. Shyness is like a veil that hides our spontaneity and natural vivacity. If we see shyness as a bad thing, we will be in a position to try and overcome it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Do not Fear Failure or Success.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Shyness often occurs as a result of our fear of failing. We worry about what people may think, so we drawback and try to hide in the background. Similar to the fear of failure is a fear of success. We are concerned that if we stand out from the crowd we will attract criticism or unwanted intrusion into our life. By hiding our real self, we can slip into anonymity. However, if we constantly prevent ourselves from revealing our true self, we will never feel satisfaction, but just cherish regrets.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Develop a oneness with others.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The root of shyness is due to the fact that we feel separated from other people. Our mind can lead us to believe that other people are quick to judge and condemn us. However, if we can change our attitude we will lose this sense of seperativity. Rather than expecting the worst from other people, identify with their good qualities. It is ironic that when we develop this sense of oneness with others, they often seek to reciprocate it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Be Yourself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If you can develop the confidence to be yourself you will not worry about what people think. Shyness is often synonymous with trying to be something we are not. The secret is to have confidence in yourself. People will generate more respect for you, when you are yourself. Speaking on shyness, Sri Chinmoy says:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;When we see a little child who is extremely shy, we feel that this child is very cute. Unfortunately, from the spiritual point of view, shyness is not a good quality at all. When you express shyness, you outwardly pretend to be what you are not, and you inwardly try to draw all the world’s admiration and attention&lt;/span&gt;." [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. Humour.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don't take life too seriously. If we happen to say slightly the wrong thing or even make a fool of ourselves, no lasting harm occurs. Many years ago, my English teacher told me that if we were nervous and shy about speaking in front of people, we should imagine they are all seated on the toilet. He argued this humorous mental image would make us smile and lighten our mood. I have never perfected this visualisation technique - such an image doesn't appeal somehow. But, I think he made a telling point that if we can force ourselves to smile and laugh, alot of our nervous tension will be released. This will reduce our shyness&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;6. Patience.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we are by nature shy, don't expect to overcome it straightaway. If we do still feel shy don't get disheartened. Try to gradually reduce the amount by which we feel shy in various circumstances.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] From: &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/sri-chinmoy-answers/part14/21.html"&gt;Sri Chinmoy Answers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digg.com/health/Howto_Overcome_Shyness"&gt;Digg This&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/how-to-overcome-shyness.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-4231853707574465426</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2007 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-19T00:12:10.786-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>happiness</category><title>How To Avoid Criticising Other People.</title><description>It is very easy to criticise other people. In fact, we may be unaware of how much time we really spend criticising other people. When we criticise people close to us, we very rarely help the other person; people don’t react positively to criticism. Quite often, when we criticise, what we are doing is bringing our own negative qualities to the fore. We may get a slight feeling of superiority, but, living in a world of gossip and criticism will bring us neither lasting peace nor happiness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The first step is to make a conscious decision to try and avoid criticising other people. Primarily, we are here thinking of the minor fault finding that the human mind is prone to making. This does not mean we will never be aware of other people’s weaknesses, instead, we are seeking to see the good in people and avoid being unnecessarily critical. Here are some suggestions to avoid criticising other people.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;1. How do we feel when we are criticised?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We have all suffered criticism at various times; it is not a pleasant experience. When we are criticised we feel miserable, defensive and angry. If we remember how we feel, we will think twice about criticising our friends and work colleagues. Empathy is a powerful invocation of our conscience. When we are aware of how much our actions can hurt others, it focuses us to avoid creating such an experience for others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Is this a fault of myself or the other person?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We are quick to judge others, but skilful to justify or ignore our own weaknesses. It is an irony that when are strongly attracted to criticising somebody’s action, we often have this own defect in our character. For example, we may say about how bad, person X, is for spreading gossip. Yet, we do not think twice about spreading this criticism to all our friends. We gossip to criticise others for gossiping; it is a blatant hypocrisy, and our human mind often fails to see the irony of our own criticism.&lt;br /&gt;When a crowd were gathering to condemn an adulterer, Jesus Christ, turned to the crowd asking. “Let the one without sin cast the first stone.” The point he was trying to make is that it is easier to condemn and criticise others, but we would be better off trying to reform our own, not insignificant, weaknesses.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Is there a better way to change our friends?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Firstly, I think it is a mistake to feel that we can change other people. But, suppose we really wish to discourage some aspect of someone else’s behaviour. Rather than directly criticising their behaviour, we can be more tactful and appeal to their better nature. For example, suppose someone is prone to being moody and miserable. If we criticise them for being miserable, they are unlikely to positively respond to this onslaught of more negativity. Instead, we can encourage them to be proactive in something that they are useful at. If they are able to prove their own self worth to themselves, this will be the best antidote to depression and unhappiness. Basically, if you want people to transcend their weaknesses, always appeal to their better nature. If we just dwell on their negative qualities, we can even make them worse rather than better.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Identify with others sufferin&lt;/span&gt;g.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sri Chinmoy suggests that one of the best ways to avoid criticising others is to develop a sense of oneness with others around you.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“When you identify yourself with the other person's suffering, you will feel, "No matter how imperfect and useless he is, I have no right to cause this kind of suffering in him. I have come into the world to establish my oneness with others and not to destroy others with my criticism."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From: &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/sri-chinmoy-answers/part7/56.html"&gt;Sri Chinmoy Library&lt;/a&gt;  in response to: Q. “How can I not criticise others and what can I do when others criticise me? Sometimes I get very mad.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;See also: &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/quotes-on-love-and-hate.html"&gt;Dealing with Anger&lt;/a&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/how-to-avoid-criticising-other-people.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-28303511758454575</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2007 20:13:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-14T13:23:45.191-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>poem</category><title>Poem: Hope Abides</title><description>&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/Lotus-with-folded-hands-Jap-776553.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/Lotus-with-folded-hands-Jap-776550.jpg" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Hope Abides&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hope abides; therefore I abide.&lt;br /&gt;Countless frustrations have not cowed me.&lt;br /&gt;I am still alive, vibrant with life.&lt;br /&gt;The black cloud will disappear,&lt;br /&gt;The morning sun will appear once again&lt;br /&gt;In all its supernal glory.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;By: Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;More &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/poetry/index.html"&gt;Poetry of Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.poetseers.org/themes/poems_hope/"&gt;Poems on Hope&lt;/a&gt; at Poetseers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Poem by: Sharani Robbins, Sri Chinmoy Centre galleries</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/poem-hope-abides.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-157495976369530507</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2007 20:40:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-10T13:44:19.073-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spirituality</category><title>What can Harry Potter teach us about Spirituality?</title><description>&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;1. Don't judge by Outer appearances&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hagrid, is, ugly, cumbersome and uncouth, with an  unfortunate fondness for dangerous animals; but, his heart is in the right place. On the other hand, who can forget the charming, but shallow, Gilderoy Lockhart? Appearing in the Chamber of Secrets, Lockhart gained a job as Master for Defence of the dark arts. Lockhart was able to impress many with his charm, beauty and extravagant tales of daring do - but this was just a cover for his lies and insecurities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Don't be distracted by Criticism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Throughout his turbulent school career, Harry gets more than his fair share of criticism. Not least, in the Order of the Phoenix when Harry is subject to much slanderous gossip. Through the eyes of others, Harry is at times hero and other times villian; but he needs to avoid being distracted by both extremes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Good Friendship&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Friendship is very important for Harry; yet, quite often, his best friends have disputes, especially Hermione and Ron. When Harry is stubborn and proud he feels miserable; when he forgives and forgets he is able to benefit from the strength of his real friendship of those close to him.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Be Courageous.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"The Soul cannot not won by the weakling." so says the Upanishads. To defeat hostile forces in life we have to face upto them with both inner and outer courage. At times we may wish to flee the battlefield of life, but, this does not solve anything. Quite often there are certain things that we need to face upto, whether we like it or not. Harry needs great courage when he is facing trials such as death eaters, Lord Voldermort, or even his own fears of death.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. Difficulties can provide opportunity for Growth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We would never invite difficulties into life, but, when they come they can be an opportunity to learn from them and grow as a person. Harry has more than his fair share of trying moments. We often feel that, although these create suffering, they also create moments of real satisfaction. The challenges Harry faces make him grow up and learn how to deal with other people.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;6. Patience&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Living with the Dursley's is torture for Harry; yet, it is also necessary. The summer holidays pass very slowly in privet Drive, and quite often Harry's patience wears thin, getting into trouble as a result.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;7. Love Thy Enemy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;True, Harry Potter does not love his enemies. The hate is easy to see - even if it is understandable. However, the character of Professor Dumbledore, gives an insight into a soul with great nobility. Dumbledore is generous with both Snape and Draco Molfoy; he hopes to bring the best out of each character. Dumbledore is willing to sacrifice his own personal safety for the effort to redeem both these characters. In this sense, Dumbledore displays a Christ like attitude of forgiving his potential enemies.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/what-can-harry-potter-teach-us-about.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-3545677410344295145</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2007 10:05:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-09-04T00:21:13.358-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>meditation</category><title>Gaining Inspiration for Meditation</title><description>&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/matterhorn-sergey-774702.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0pt 10px 10px 0pt; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/matterhorn-sergey-774700.jpg" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;THere are many ways to gain inspiration for meditation. If we meditate with other people this will help. There are &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog/meditation/improving-your-meditation/"&gt;several ways to improve your meditation here&lt;/a&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/gaining-inspiration-for-meditation.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7116191939527158910</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2007 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-07T03:22:08.269-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>meditation</category><title>Improving Your Meditation</title><description>&lt;a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/white-geranium400-758508.jpg"&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer;" src="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/uploaded_images/white-geranium400-758506.jpg" alt="" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Whatever standard of our meditation we can always find some new techniques to give us better and more fulfilling meditation. The real secret of meditation is to feel that we are always an eternal beginner. If we have this attitude it will be easier to empty the mind.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Read books by Spiritual Teachers and great seekers&lt;/span&gt;. When we read about the highest experiences of others we get a lot of encouragement and inspiration to try and attain these profound experiences ourselves. For example reading the Gospel of Sri Ramakrishna or “Autobiography of a Yogi” by Paramahansa Yogananda” will give an insight into the divine experiences of these 2 great Saints. They cannot help but inspire our own meditation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Try a new Meditation Exercise.&lt;/span&gt; There are many different types of meditation exercises. If you are struggling with the same one it is good to try something a little different. For example you could just incorporate this simple pranayama exercise into the start of your meditation, it is called 1 – 4 –2 . When you breathe in repeat the name of God (or some mantra that inspires you) once. Then hold your breathe for four counts. Then as you exhale repeat your mantra twice. This will energise your entire being and quieten the mind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. Place great Intensity on your meditation.&lt;/span&gt; One thing we can try is to feel that this is our last day, our last opportunity to meditate. If we only had 1 more chance to meditate we wouldn’t waste it thinking about what to eat for tomorrow’s breakfast. Each time we meditate we should feel nothing else is important.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Set yourself Goals.&lt;/span&gt; For a week you could say every day I will meditate at 6.30pm for half an hour. If we set targets and stick to them we will definitely get more from a regular practise of meditation. If we have no regularity and meditate only when we can find time, often we find that several days can pass by without meditating.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. Remember a Profound Meditation.&lt;/span&gt; If we have been practising meditation for a while we should try to visualize a really powerful meditation we had in the past. Imagination has its own power by visualising a high experience we can experience it again and also go beyond.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;If you enter into the world of imagination and stay there for 10 or 15 mins, power will automatically enter into your mediation, and it will bear fruit. Then it will not be imagination at all; you will actually be deep in the world of meditation.&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;6. Meditate with Music.&lt;/span&gt; Spiritual, soulful music will elevate our aspiring consciousness. It will bring our heart and soul to the fore. This will make our meditation much more powerful, we will easily go beyond the activity of the mind and into the domain of the soul.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;7. Make a really beautiful shrine.&lt;/span&gt; If we can create a sacred corner where we only meditate, we will be able to build up a powerful meditative vibration. If we decorate our shrine with beautiful flowers and candles, it will give us an added iota of inspiration in our meditation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;8. Never Give Up. &lt;/span&gt;If we feel that our meditation was not particularly good, we should not feel disappointed. If we judge our own progress negatively we will lose our inspiration to meditate. We should feel that each time we sit down to meditate we are making necessary progress even if outwardly we can’t see it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/resources/meditation.html"&gt;Meditation pages&lt;/a&gt; at Sri Chinmoy Bio&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/articles/meditation-beginners.html"&gt;Meditation for Beginners&lt;/a&gt; - Article on beginning meditation</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/improving-your-meditation.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-5086660498066793949</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2007 21:37:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-03T14:44:19.834-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spiritual masters</category><title>Ramana Maharshi: Who am I?</title><description>&lt;img src="http://srichinmoybio.co.uk/seers/images/ramana.jpg" class="alignleft"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ramana Maharshi was a spiritual Master, who spent most of his life around the holy mountain of Arunachala in South India. Ramana Maharshi, played a pivotal role in indirectly introducing meditation and yoga into the West. His life and teachings were of great simplicity; focusing on the philosophy of advaita Vedanta.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As a young boy, Ramana Maharshi had an ordinary upbringing; however, around the age of 16 he became obsessed with fear about death. The young Ramana became paralysed with fear about what would happen on dying. This experiences changed his outlook on life; he no longer could gain satisfaction from wordly activities, instead he became absorbed in seeking a deeper meaning to life. He shunned his former activies and on one day resolved to leave his school, home and family so that he could put all his energies into meditation and yoga. For several years Ramana lived the life of a wandering ascetic; he spent most of his time in prayer and mediation and was magnetically drawn to the holy mountain of Arunachala. In the early years of his sadhana, Ramana lived amongst the wild creatures of the mountain. Ramana Maharshi never showed any fear to animals, his spiritual realisation gave him a uniques sense of oneness with other creatures.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For several years, he lived at Arunachala in relative anonymity; but over time he began to attract sincere seekers who felt in him a magnetic spiritual force of peace and illumination. As the number of disciples increased, a simple ashram was developed on the hills of Arunachala. It was here that Ramana Maharshi spent the remainder of his days. He spoke rarely, he preferred to teach through the silence of his meditation. Quite often seekers would come with a flood of questions, only to find them answered when they sat in the meditation hall.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ramana Maharshi did write down some of his philosophy and spiritual teachings. They are characterised by a simplicity and clarity that directs a seekers straight to the source. The main suggestion of Ramana Maharshi was for seekers to concentrate on answering the question. "Who am I?" - If we can answer this question and discover our real self, all our problems would be solved. Ramana Mahashi taught that the only way to satisfactorily answer this question was through meditation. He encouraged aspirants to try and trace the place where thoughts come from. If we relentlessly follow thoughts back to their source, we come to learn that we are not our thoughts. Our sense of "I" ness will change from the limited ego, to the all encompassing universal soul. Sri Chinmoy says , from a spiritual perspective, the question of "Who am I? is by far the most significant question we can ask.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"Ultimately, all the questions that philosophy asks can be reduced to "Who am I?" Then the reply comes spontaneously, "Who am I not?" The question and the answer may be found at the same place." [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many visitors came to meditate in the presence of Ramana Maharshi. Often visitors would come with a flood of question; however, on sitting in the meditation hall there questions would be answered in silence. This was the experience of Paul Brunton, an Englishman seeking the meaning of life. Paul Brunton wrote down many of his Indian experiences in a book "Search in Secret India." This helped to introduce the idea of meditation to western society.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;Philosophy - Wisdom Chartiot&lt;/span&gt; at Sri Chinmoy Library&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://srichinmoybio.co.uk/seers/ramana_maharshi_quotes.html"&gt;Ramana Maharshi Quotes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Related posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/discovering-meaning-of-life.html"&gt;The Meaning of Life&lt;/a&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/ramana-maharshi-who-am-i.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-5960499185881689443</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2007 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-07-03T14:09:38.182-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>self transcendence</category><title>Why do you watch TV?</title><description>Whenever man achieves something, new, difficult and challenging, quite often the response of society is Why?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Why climb Mount Everest? Why Run a marathon? Why run a &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/3100-mile-self-transcendence-race.html"&gt;3100 mile race&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Within humans there are often 2 conflicting forces. The first instinct is our desire for conformity and to live an easy life. After all, life has enough difficulties without adding to them. Therefore, we seek to live according to the customs and norms of society. Without realising it, much of our action and thought is based on the conventional wisdom of the society we happen to be born into. To step outside this conventional wisdom, is like challenging preconceived ideas of what is acceptable and not. Pathfinders often meet with skepticism, criticism and even hostility; people are often skeptical of things that are new and different.  Part of the reason is that people can feel threatened when others offer a new perspective on life. Therefore, to avoid the criticism and the skepticism of others, we seek to avoid conflict and live a "normal" life. Sometimes this decision is conscious, but quite often we may just live a certain way without fully considering why or whether this is the best path.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;However, although this instinct for conformity is strong, there is another motivating force in man. This is the desire for improving ourself - our conscious evolution and self-transcendence. In many ways, man is evolving and seeking for a better way to do things. In athletics we aspire to go faster; in science we aspire for greater technological advances. There is also an inner quest to aspire for something new and more fulfilling. It may be hard to say why, but there is something inside us that is not satisfied with what we have. It is this driving force, which motivates us to take a new challenge. It is this inspiration which encourages to try something new and unique. We want to climb everest, simply because we have not done it before. There may be no material reward for climbing a mountain; but in achieving such a feat we get a tremendous sense of satisfaction that cannot be gained in ordinary activities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The problem with an easy life of material comforts is that it does not give us lasting satisfaction. We can get a limited happiness and a limited pleasure, but the happiness is often fleeting and dependent on external factors. When we go beyond our self imposed limitations we learn that there is a deeper meaning to both life and our self. Through setting challenges and transcending ourselves we get tremendous joy. This can be difficult to explain to others; people may see only the outer discomforts of running a marathon. Someone who has never run a marathon cannot fully appreciate the experience. Yet, it quite often doesn't stop them passing judgement on the action. From a certain perspective it may be daft to spend 2 months running a 3100 mile race. But, at the same time, they cannot have a true appreciation of the experience of others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"Because it's there."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Is it necessary to justify feats of self transcendence to others? Edmund Hilary, climbed Mount Everest because it was there. Do we need a better reason? We could ask ourselves why do spend many hours doing nothing much in particular. Why do we watch TV? Because it's there? No matter how much TV we watch there is only so much satisfaction and joy we can derive. There comes a time when we may ask ourselves Why spend all day watching TV? Why not so something else.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In truth we rarely ask why we do anything. Much of our action is automatic; we do it just because it is easy to do. We may not be able to justify our attempt to climb mount Everest, but at the same time we may not be able to justify our decision to spend many hours watching TV.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/07/why-do-you-watch-tv.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-1537351034857887149</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2007 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-25T09:08:06.604-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spirituality</category><title>Discovering the Meaning of Life</title><description>The meaning of life is the perpetual question that has perplexed humanity since the dawn of man's evolution. As one might expect, numerous theories have been suggested as to the real meaning of life. Yet theories and philosophies cannot satisfy our aspiration to know the hidden secrets of life. In essence, the meaning of life is a quest that can only be discovered by the person themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Who am I?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In spirituality we find there is actually only one question that we really need to ask: who am I? If we can know who we are all our problems and uncertainties will be solved. But, to know who we are is much more difficult than we may actually imagine. The natural response is to consider ourselves identified with the body and mind. But the body is perishable, and the mind is a volatile and temperamental collection of transient thoughts. The great sage Ramana Maharshi taught that to discover who we are, we should keep asking the question who am I? However, Ramana Maharshi also taught that the answer would not be another mere collection of thoughts. By constantly asking the question who am I? we seek to dive deep down to where the thought originates from. By asking this question, we come to learn that we are not just our thoughts. At the heart of our existence is the real I, which can decide whether to pursue or reject thoughts. In discovering who am I? we learn that we are not the little I identified with our ego; instead the real "I" is a consciousness far greater than our ego can understand.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"In the ordinary life each human being has millions and millions of questions to ask. In his spiritual life, a day dawns when he feels that there is only one question worth asking: "Who am I?" The answer of answers is: "I am not the body, but I am the Inner Pilot."&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sri Chinmoy  [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Meditation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The path of self enquiry is a certain type of meditation. It is through meditation that we can go beyond the realm of the mind to discover the spiritual aspect of ourselves. We may find meditation difficult in the beginning, but, through practising concentration and meditation techniques, we eventually learn to stop the mind completely. If we can attain a state of consciousness free of thought, we will look upon the world with a new perspective. Through being unencumbered with thoughts, we discover the limitations of the mind; we also learn of the inner joy that is not dependent on our outer circumstances.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Social Conditioning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is great power in social conditioning. The way we are brought up reflects our perspective of life. We tend to feel that what society and our family expect is what we should follow. If we are brought up in one way, we often feel that this must be the best way; people either do not want, or cannot, question the ingrained orthodoxy of life. The great philosophical appeal of Socrates was that he taught people to question everything, even if that means going against the grain of popular opinion. To discover the meaning of life we have to be ready to question and, if necessary, jettison our long cherished beliefs. There is a Zen analogy, that we cannot fill a glass that is already full. If we wish to fill the glass with knowledge, we first have to empty it of our existing beliefs. Similarly, if we empty the mind, only then can we fill it with spiritual knowledge on the meaning of life.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Discovering the meaning of life is a life long process, it cannot be reduced to a philosophical mathematical formula (although 42 was not a bad effort *). The meaning of life is not something that can be forced on others, it is really synonymous with the discovery of our higher self,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;References:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1]&lt;a href="ttp://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/yoga-spiritual-life/2.html"&gt; Yoga and the Spiritual Life&lt;/a&gt; at Sri Chinmoy Library&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/peace-pilgrim/1.html"&gt;The Meaning of Life&lt;/a&gt; at Sri Chinmoy Library&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Off Topic Musings on the Meaning of Life&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;* In Hitch Hikers Guide to the Galaxy, Deep Thought returned an answer of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Answer_to_Life%2C_the_Universe%2C_and_Everything"&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/discovering-meaning-of-life.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-2772027076878070287</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2007 10:09:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-24T03:14:09.049-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spiritual perspective</category><title>What does a Red Traffic Light Mean to You?</title><description>Whenever I fly to New York I cannot help but notice all the adverts for HSBC, "the local global bank", or something like that. What impresses me is that they show how the same thing can give either a very good or very bad connotation, depending on our frame of mind / social conditioning. Just for one example, the idea of 2 weeks lying on a beach is my idea of a terribly boring holiday. At the same time, others may find a cycling tour through the swiss Alps, perfect hell.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are many things that we consider to be a bad thing, but is it actually fair to maintain this attitude? Is it possible to see good things in everything?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For example, my instinctive feeling is that a red traffic light is a bad thing: it delays our progress, it is a waste of time. If all our lights are green then we feel the Gods are smiling on us. If all the traffic light are red, we feel perfectly miserable and become convinced the whole world is conspiring against us. As a cyclist, a red light at a pedestrian crossing, only creates a temptation to ignore it and cycle through anyway.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Reading this essay from Everest Aspiration, by Sri Chinmoy, inspired me to look upon red traffic lights in another light(pardon the pun)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"The red stoplight discourages me when I am in a hurry. The same red light soothes my life when I am not in a hurry..." [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Instead of seeing a red light as an obstacle on the journey, it is an opportunity to be mentally still, not exactly meditation; but rather than entertaining thoughts of frustrations and impatience I can, at least, try to hold neutral / positive thoughts. A red light is not a meaningless obstacle but a necessary item to allow a smooth journey.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The great spiritual traditions teach us that real happiness is not dependent on external circumstances. Real happiness stems from our state of mind. Whatever may befall us in the outer life, it is our inner attitude that determines whether it is a good thing or not. We may go through life, metaphorically praying all the traffic lights will be green, but God may not want to fulfil this desire. If we pray for all obstacles to be cleared we will never learn that even red traffic lights can be an opportunity for reflection, inner poise and an inner self transcendence.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So even commercial adverts can have a scope for spiritual instruction, it just shows that our mental perceptions will determine our outlook quite significantly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1]  &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/sri-chinmoy-everest-aspiration/part3/11.html"&gt;The Red Stoplight&lt;/a&gt; - essay by Sri Chinmoy: from Everest Aspiration Part 3 by Sri Chinmoy.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/what-does-red-traffic-light-mean-to-you.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-5990404819199318662</guid><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2007 16:56:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-20T09:56:45.769-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>stress</category><title>Dealing With Stress</title><description>Stress occurs because we struggle to deal with issues as they arise. Stress seems to be an almost inevitable part of modern life; the pace and demands of our modern lifestyle leave little scope for relaxation. However, if we can learn to let go of stress we can easily become more productive and enjoy life much more.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These are some suggestions for reducing stress.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Don't create More Problems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we have many difficult issues from work, we should not create additional demands on our time, like deciding to move house. Wait until one issue is resolved before starting on more difficult issues.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Don't Create Arguments with Other people.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alot of stress comes from disagreements with other people. However, if we are careful we can avoid alot of these unnecessary personality disputes. If people do something we disagree with, then we can just ignore it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Don't feel responsible for Other People.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we are honest we have more than enough difficulties in our own life, without worrying about other people's problems. If we feel responsible for solving other people's problems we are, in a way, inviting unsolvable problems into our life, which can only increase our stress levels. If people come to us for advice, we can offer it. However, we cannot be responsible for the life of others, even if they are a close relation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Don't Exaggerate our Difficulties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Often when we feel stressed, we feel there is no end in sight. Our mind tends to magnify our difficulties and make them appear bigger than they actually are. We should be careful about not following trains of thought, that only add to our stress. As&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/"&gt; Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt; suggests on the power of thought:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The ordinary human mind&lt;br /&gt;Is a container.&lt;br /&gt;You can fill it&lt;br /&gt;With good thoughts&lt;br /&gt;Or bad thoughts.&lt;br /&gt;It is up to you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;(1)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;What is Important?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we feel very stressed it is a sign we are not happy with a certain situation. If we are stressed about money issues maybe, in the long term, there are different strategies. For example, do we need to continue working in a high paid job, which places great demands on our time? Do we really need a second job?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Meditation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Meditation can undoubtedly be a boon for reducing our stress levels. Stress is always related to an overburdened mind; it can be difficult to switch off from our daily problems. However, if we practise meditation we can help ourselves to let go of our mental problems, even if for a short time. One meditation exercise that we can try, is to leave the mind and enter the heart. We can visualise ourselves leaving the mind and becoming aware of a consciousness inside our heart. If helpful, we can visualise a peaceful scene, such as, by an expanse of sea. If we are able to focus our sense of awareness on the heart, our thoughts will have less power; over time we can develop the art of not listening to our thoughts at all. This will give us a real sense of inner peace and relaxation. This is a powerful antitode to the stresses of the mind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Related blog Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sumangali.org/2007/05/commuting-meditation.html"&gt;Commuting Meditation&lt;/a&gt; at Sumangali.org&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/art-of-happiness.html"&gt;The Art of Happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/what-gardening-can-teach-us-about.html"&gt;What Gardening can teach us about happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class="copyright"&gt;(1) Excerpt from &lt;i&gt;Twenty-Seven Thousand Aspiration-Plants, Part 3&lt;/i&gt; by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;/span&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/dealing-with-stress.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-4454057961093329274</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2007 21:35:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-19T09:24:21.332-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>time</category><title>How to Find More Time in the Day.</title><description>How would you like the idea of a 26 hour day or 3 day weekend? In recent years western society has witnessed a significant growth in Economic prosperity and living standards; however, there has been little if any increase in spare time. If anything people struggle, more than ever, to find time for the elusive boon of more time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These are some innovative ideas to help make better use of time in the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;1. Don't sleep more than necessary.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;People differ in their requirements for sleep. However, it is easy to sleep for longer than you may need. The mind is prone to lethargy, especially early in the morning. We need to be disciplined to get up early in the morning, so that we will not lose precious hours. The secret to getting up early is to develop a regularity; this can involve a regular time for awakening, which you keep even at the weekends.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;2. Don't try to do Several things at Once.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sometimes we feel that if we try to do several things at once, we will be able to complete more than we anticipate. However, what often happens is that we are unable to focus on any particular object. Instead we tend to get stressed and struggle to complete anything satisfactorily. If we take things one step at a time, we will have more focus and will be able to get things done quickly and efficiently, leaving more time for other things.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;3. See Every Moment as an Opportunity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some things appear beyond our control, however, we can turn many of these things into a productive process. Travel is a big aspect of people's lives; commuting to work can take up to 2 or 3 hours. Therefore, it can be a big burden on our time. If we are thoughtful we will be able to turn commuting time into productive time. For example, if we want more time for exercise, we could try to walk or cycle part of the journey. On the other hand, using a laptop enables us to work whilst travelling by train or coach.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;4. Can we work Less?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is a growing phenomena in the West of people developing an addiction to work. Basically, it means that people are always looking for extra things to do. Rather than just completing the necessary tasks, we find extra things to fill our time. This may stem from a desire for perfection, or it may just be that work becomes the easiest thing to do. However, we should feel the necessity and importance of creating time for things outside work. This may involve leaving some less important tasks half undone. If we aim for perfection in everything, we will never have the time for anything else.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;5. Get rid of superfluous activities.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is surprising how much time we can spend in doing unproductive tasks. It is easy to reduce the time we spending watching the news and checking email. If we are not careful it is easy to waste time such as: watching the same news items several times, or watching TV - but only because nothing else is on.&lt;br /&gt;This does not mean we want to have no time for relaxation and enjoyment. It just means we avoid doing useless things that give us neither relaxation or enjoyment.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/how-to-find-more-time-in-day.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7772154792815626586</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2007 10:08:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-09T03:26:34.487-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>happiness</category><title>What Gardening can teach us about happiness</title><description>It is said Gardening is one of the best ways to be happy, what can gardening teach us about the art of being happy?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Be Patient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For a seed to germinate, sprout and flower can take several months. As gardener's we do not expect instant success. In modern life we often expect and desire things as soon as possible, and when they feel to materialise, we feel miserable. We often lack the patience for things to arrive at the due time. However, if like a gardener, we can cultivate patience we will be able remain cheerful at all times.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;Happiness in life I need. &lt;br /&gt;But alas, without patience,&lt;br /&gt;My happiness remains always&lt;br /&gt;A far cry.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Value the Journey not just the Goal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A gardener enjoys the whole process of gardening, from planting seeds to watching the plant grow and flower. If a gardener only got joy when plants flowered, he would miss out on a whole aspect of gardening. In life we should not just aim for results or achievements; we can get happiness from our participation and preparation. Happiness comes not through being dependent on outer success and receiving things; happiness is dependent on our attitude to whatever we are doing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Everything has its season.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sometimes we want to capture a moment of happiness. We think that happiness is something to be treasured and held onto.When our happiness is dependent upon this kind of attachment, we are doomed to experience frustration and disappointment. Nothing in the world is permanent, everything comes and goes. However, this does not mean we cannot remain happy. In autumn a gardener does not become despondent because plants die back. He knows that this is what is expected;  he also knows that next year will bring new life and new growth, possibly better than the previous year. The great spiritual teachings teach us to retain an attitude of detachment at fluctuations of the world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;For everything there is a season,&lt;br /&gt;and a time for every matter under heaven:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; a time to be born,&lt;br /&gt;and a time to die;&lt;br /&gt; a time to plant,&lt;br /&gt;and a time to pluck up what is planted;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ecclesiastes 3:1-18; NRS [2]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;From Winter Comes Spring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At times life may feel like a barren desert, but no matter how bad life may seem it will not remain like this forever. Sometimes dark periods come and it is hard to see a way through; however, all periods of darkness are temporary. To get through these periods of unhappiness, we can let go of negative thoughts and concentrate only on positive thoughts. We should not contemplate on the present fallow period but look forward to the brighter future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Tolerance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The qualities of trees and plants are self giving, patience and beauty. No matter how people treat a tree, it continues to offer its shade. When offering its qualities of shade and patience a tree doesn't judge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;How to achieve happiness?&lt;br /&gt;Not by giving, not by talking,&lt;br /&gt;But by being.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [2]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Similarly, if we avoid judging others we will benefit from much greater happiness. When we judge others we bring in the critical mind, it is hard to cultivate happiness when the critical mind dominates.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;references&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] Excerpt from Twenty-Seven Thousand Aspiration-Plants, Part 224 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;[2] Ecclesiastes, NT&lt;br /&gt;[3] Excerpt from Seventy-Seven Thousand Service-Trees, Part 4 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Related posts:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/art-of-happiness.html"&gt;The Art of Happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.debramoorhead.com/blog/?p=196"&gt;What Gardening has taught me about Life&lt;/a&gt; by Debra Moorhead</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/what-gardening-can-teach-us-about.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-1944469134918803942</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2007 21:19:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-06T15:13:52.930-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>meditation</category><title>Different Stages of Meditation</title><description>&lt;strong&gt;1. Curiosity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The first stage of meditation is learning about what it involves. Some people may have preconceived notions of what meditation is; for example, people may associate meditation with sitting in various yoga postures. However, meditation is primarily the art of silencing the mind and discovering our inner self. Whatever books we read about meditation, it will share this common theme of going beyond the mind and raising our consciousness. However, no matter how much we read and talk about meditation, it is only when we practise meditation that we discover its real meaning.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Relaxation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we first attempt to meditate we need to learn how to be still and relax the body and mind. Some people may actually find it quite hard to sit perfectly still for 20-30 minutes. However, this is essential to meditation. If we cannot keep the body still, we cannot hope to still the mind. After relaxing the body we can then seek to improve our mental relaxation. We are usually used to carrying around a burden of worries and anxieties; we find it difficult to relax. However, the preliminary stage of meditation is to let go of these tension; we learn to forget the past and future and just focus on the present moment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Concentration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nearly all beginners to meditation find that when they try to meditate, they become aware of how busy the mind is. Therefore, the most important thing, to learn and practise, is how to silence the mind. To do this we need to learn the art of concentration. This means to focus on one thing at a time. When we can develop the capacity to focus our awareness on one thing at a time, it means that we will be able to make progress in meditation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Detached from Thoughts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is difficult to detach ourselves completely from our thoughts. However, there is an intermediary stage where we become aware of our thoughts, but they feel very distant. It is like we are aware of thoughts in the background. However, because we don't give them priority, they feel separated from our consciousness. They are like fish in the sea, which swim past, but don't really disturb us. When our thoughts appear external and separate, it becomes much easier to enter a state of real meditation&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Silent Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Real silent meditation occurs when we can stop any thought entering. When we meditate in real inner silence we will unmistakably feel an expansion of our consciousness. What actually happens is that when we stop the mind we can become aware of the consciousness of our own soul. It is meditation that enables us to experience the divine qualities of peace and joy in abundant measure. These aspects are part of everyone's nature; but, it is meditation that makes them accessible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When you meditate, what you actually do is to enter into a calm or still, silent mind. We have to be fully aware of the arrival and attack of thoughts. That is to say, we shall not allow any thought, divine or undivine, good or bad, to enter into our mind. Our mind should be absolutely silent.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Samadhi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When our aspiration is intense and our mind completely clear, it is possible to experience very high states of meditation known as samadhi. To explain what is meant by samadhi is really an impossible task. By their very nature, these states of consciousness are far beyond the domain of the intellectual mind. Words can never explain or describe concepts of infinity and immortality. To gain an insight into samadhi it is best to read the writings of a realised spiritual Master, who has actually experienced them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;"When we meditate, we try to expand ourselves, like a bird spreading its wings. We try to expand our finite consciousness and enter into the Universal Consciousness where there is no fear, jealousy or doubt but only joy, peace and divine power."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] What Is Meditation?... Excerpt from Earth's Cry Meets Heaven's Smile, Part 1 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[2] &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoy.org/spirituality/concentration_meditation_contemplation/meditation/meditation__glimpsing_the_infinite"&gt;Meditation: Glimpsing the Infinite&lt;/a&gt;</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/different-stages-of-meditation.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-2767163779849385872</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2007 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-08-15T08:53:42.927-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>happiness</category><title>The Art of Happiness</title><description>Happiness is at times an elusive phenomena. In many ways we strive for greater happiness, but often the more we grasp, the more difficult it becomes. Yet, the great Saints and spiritual traditions suggest joy and happiness are an integral part of our real Self.  If we can be discover our own highest self, happiness will become a spontaneous experience, independent of the fluctuations of the world. These are some suggestions for cultivating real happiness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Minimise Desires&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Quite often we feel that if certain desires can be fulfilled all our problems will be solved. For example, we may think that if only we can get a better job and bigger car, then we will be happy. However, usually when one desire is fulfilled it just creates new desires. Monetary gain can give temporary happiness, but it is no guarantee for permanent satisfaction. If we can minimise desires, we can learn to be cultivate happiness whatever happens in the outer world. Simplicity enables us to enjoy the moment, rather than always looking forward to a better tomorrow.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Man's sincere desire:   &lt;br /&gt;Grasp, possess and enjoy quickly.  &lt;br /&gt;The soul's sincere desire:  &lt;br /&gt;Aspire, offer and enjoy eternally.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="http://priyadarshan.org/sri-chinmoy"&gt;Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Excerpt from Ten Thousand Flower-Flames, Part 5 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Criticism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Happiness can never be found in world criticism. At times our criticism may be justified, but, if we are honest, our criticism does little to change other people and the world situation. If we spend time criticising others, our mind will be filled with negative thoughts. If we really value happiness we will not have time to be a negative critic. True, the world has teeming imperfections, but, if we really wish to be happy, we should begin by trying to improve ourselves. Quite often when we are criticising others, we are actually only highlighting our own faults.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Appreciation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Instead of looking at the faults of our friends, we should try to appreciate their good qualities. Others will definitely appreciate this generous attitude. People tend to respond in the way they are treated. If we treat others with respect they will subconsciously seek to reciprocate it. Appreciation of other's good qualities does not mean false flattery. Outwardly we may not say anything, but we will forgive and forget their mistakes, and always seek to bring out their good qualities; this is one of the most effective ways for cultivating happiness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;Judge nothing&lt;br /&gt;You will be happy.&lt;br /&gt;Forgive everything&lt;br /&gt;You will be happier.&lt;br /&gt;Love everything&lt;br /&gt;You will be the happiest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Look after the Body.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is possible to be happy,whatever ails the body. However, we can make life easier if we seek to avoid unnecessary health complications. Keeping fit helps both the mind and body. Being active prevents boredom and stimulates the mind. Also, avoiding unnecessary intoxicants will similarly keep the mind and body in good shape. When we overindulge in stimulants such as alcohol and drugs, any fleeting pleasure is followed by pain and hangover. We should never feel our happiness depends on taking various chemical substances.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Be active.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thomas Jefferson said the secret of his happiness was the fact he was both busy and maintained an inner poise.&lt;br /&gt;    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;" It is neither wealth nor splendor; but tranquillity and occupation which give happiness. "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;[2]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we have little focus and little to aim for, we tend to become self absorbed in small, petty problems. If we have alot to do, then we do not have time to be worried and annoyed by small things. An easy, carefree life is no guarantee of happiness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Meditation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The aim of meditation is discover the real happiness within. Meditation is the art of silencing the mind, so that our Soul can come to the fore. When our mind is filled with countless thoughts it is difficult to experience any inner peace. At best our mind gives only a fleeting happiness. Meditation expands our consciousness so we are not limited by the thoughts of the mind. It is meditation that enables us to live in the soul.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;"True inner joy is self-created.&lt;br /&gt;It does not depend on outer circumstances&lt;br /&gt;Or outer achievements."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/srichinmoy/biography.html"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt;, [3]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] The Goal is Won, Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;[2] Thomas Jefferson Selected quotes&lt;br /&gt;[3] Sri Chinmoy, The Wings of Joy</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/art-of-happiness.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-3356149292379944598</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2007 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-06-02T06:04:10.889-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>oneness</category><title>What Unites and What separates People?</title><description>&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Heart and Mind.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The real divisions occur when we use our mind to judge and criticise others. It is the proud judgements of the mind which create feelings of inferiority and superiority, and therefore, division. If we use the power of the heart we gain a feeling of oneness. It is in the heart where we can bring to the fore the qualities of forgiveness and compassion. When we look at the world with a forgiving and loving attitude, we do not create division. Living in the heart, we seek to be aware of an underlying unity and oneness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Religion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Religion is quite often an instrument used for creating division. When a religion unmistakably feels that, it alone, is the true path to God, division naturally arises. Adherents of some religions feel that only by proclaiming a certain faith, can one be granted salvation. Such a belief inevitably leads to a feeling of superiority; the followers may feel under a compulsion to convert and save others, who have not accepted their particular branch of religion. When religion places all priority on philosophical belief and outer forms, there can seem to be an unbridgeable gap between one religion and the next. Such divisive views can become a pretext for both religious persecution and religious wars.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;However, we cannot condemn religion just because it can sometimes be used to assert feelings of superiority. When we seek to discover the essence of religion, we find that the heart of religion is not outer dogma, but; spiritual practice, love of God and the search for Truth. When we go deep within, through prayer and meditation, religion becomes a mechanism to discover our real self. Practising religion from a purely spiritual perspective, shows us that spiritual realisation is dependent, not on our intellectual beliefs, but our inner aspiration and attitude.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"If we live in our oneness-heart, we will feel the essence of all religions which is the love of God. Forgiveness, compassion, tolerance, brotherhood and the feeling of oneness are the signs of a true religion."&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many great saints and sages have taught that although the paths are many, the goal is the same. Each religion can lead a seeker to God. The Truth can be approached from different angles; people may call God by different names; but this doesn't change or alter the fundamental nature of truth.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thus genuine religious experience does not divide, but can teach the fundamental oneness of life and the Universe&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Nationalism and Patriotism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"Patriotism is your conviction that this country is superior to all others because you were born in it"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- George Bernard Shaw.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nationalism divides when a country feels the need to assert its supremacy. When a country wishes to assert its ideology and values over others, there can be no peace or oneness. Aggressive nationalism also springs from a subconscious feeling of inadequacy or fear. We fear other countries and people, because we feel a sense of weakness. Because of this fear we build walls of separation. Yet, these fears are usually borne of ignorance and lack of knowledge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;However, patriotism need not be divisive. A true patriot does not feel the necessity of asserting his superiority. Real patriotism means holding a love for your country. However, this faith does not mean we fear other countries. When we have a sincere love for our own country, our oneness heart can easily extend to the rest of the world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"Patriotism is self-enlargement, self-expansion and, at the same time, self-giving to the source. This self-enlargement takes place in the divine way; it is not enlargement of ego. The self-giving and self-offering of patriotism come from the feeling that other countries can derive some light from your own country's awakening. Patriotism is self-giving and self-expansion based on your conscious oneness with all consciousness, your inseparable oneness with all. That is the meaning of patriotism in the spiritual sense.&lt;/span&gt;"&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [2]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Oneness does not require uniformity. Unity in diversity is not a mere philosophical platitude. Sincere patriotism is perfectly compatible with breaking down barriers between countries.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The effects of religion, patriotism e.t.c depend on how we look upon them. Anything can be used to create division. At the same time, if we aspire for union, if we aspire for unity in the heart, then we will not create excuses for building division with others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;by: Tejvan Pettinger 01/06/07&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/world-destruction-impossible/part1/15.html"&gt;Religion&lt;/a&gt; - Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[2] &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoylibrary.com/love-country-purity-body/2.html"&gt;Spirituality and Patriotism&lt;/a&gt; Excerpt from I Love My Country: Purity's Body by Sri Chinmoy.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/06/what-unites-and-what-separates-people.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-7923443816438690375</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2007 21:29:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-05-31T14:43:13.920-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>happiness</category><title>How To Overcome Depression</title><description>Depression and unhappiness is a miserable experience. There is nothing worse than a feeling of depression, we should seek to try and avoid depression as much as possible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To Overcome Depression there are a number of things that we can try and do.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Do not Dwell on Depressed Thoughts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If we always ruminate over our depressed mindset it will be very difficult, if not impossible, to overcome our depression. Our thoughts influence our state of mind very strongly. Sometimes our depressed thoughts can appear quite powerful, but we need to try and let go of them. If we constantly say no to negative and depressed thoughts, there will come a time when they will stop bothering us.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Focus on Positive Things.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If it is difficult to stop negative thoughts occurring, another suggestion is to focus on good, inspiring, uplifting thoughts. When we feel depressed, we should force ourselves to think about something good. This can either be about somebody else, or something we have achieved in the past. When we are depressed we may feel to entertain such thoughts is useless. But, even if we are unsuccessful in the beginning, these good thoughts will slowly percolate through our mind. It will have a positive effect over time, even if we don't expect it to.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Be Active&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One of the best cures for depression is to engage in various activities. When we are busy our mind does not have time to dwell on a depressed train of thought. Physical exercise can be particularly helpful; this is because when we exercise we release serotonin, a helpful chemical for improving state of mind Quite often, when we are depressed we do not feel like doing anything. Therefore, we need to try and force ourselves to go and do something. It may be help to do things with others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Speak to Others&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we share problems and worries with other people, we can unburden a significant cause of our depression. When we discuss things with others, it helps us to get a sense of perspective. It is important to be able to find someone who will be a good listener. We shouldn't expect others to solve our problems for us. But, at the same time we should feel that we do not need to be entirely self-sufficient.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Be Positive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It might be difficult, but we should try to be positive and sincerely seek to throw off our depression. It is a mistake to encourage sympathy and feelings of self-pity. When we attract others to console us, it will not cut off the root of depression; in fact it can often feed the depression.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Find the Joy Within.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Our real nature is joy, if we can access the soul we can experience this inner joy, which is the underlying essence of our being. When we are depressed we should feel that this is a false reflection of our nature. We should feel the necessity of going beyond this temporary state and bringing to the fore our inner happiness. Also, it is important to have confidence in our self. Our true nature can overcome depression.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"...&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt; the strength of the soul's will is far greater than the strength of these undivine forces. If you can bring forward even one percent of your soul's willpower, with that you will be able to conquer your depression.&lt;/span&gt;"&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Smile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Even if the smile is false and forced it may help a little. When we smile we can have a positive effect on our state of mind. The more we smile and laugh the easier it is to overcome depression.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] How to Illumine Depression by Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Article by &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/links/contact.html"&gt;R.Pettinger&lt;/a&gt; May 2007.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/how-to-overcome-depression.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-3291381750553636066</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2007 21:23:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-05-31T14:25:09.821-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>reincarnation</category><title>The Cycle of Reincarnation Explained</title><description>&lt;strong&gt;The Purpose of Reincarnation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Reincarnation is the idea that death is not the end. After death the soul leaves the body, but, after a temporary rest takes rebirth in a new body. Reincarnation is an integral belief of many spiritual traditions. It is often asked why is reincarnation necessary? The main reason is that Reincarnation gives the soul chance to make slow steady progress towards fulfilling its highest goals.&lt;br /&gt;Different Experiences.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From each incarnation the soul takes the quintessence of its experiences. From these different episodes in the evolution of the soul, it is possible to gain a comprehensive understanding of many different experiences. In one incarnation we may have great fame, wealth and power. However, even in this kind of incarnation, we cannot achieve peace of mind and abiding satisfaction. Therefore, in our next lifetime we may have a more ordinary, humble incarnation. We will view life from perspective of both powerful and weak. This will give us greater understanding. These different experiences also give us the opportunity to fulfil our desires.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In one lifetime on earth we cannot do everything…Now our dearest is God. Do you think that God will allow us to remain unfulfilled? No! God's very purpose is to fulfil each individual and Himself through us. He will have us come back again and again to fulfil our desires.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fresh Start.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After a certain number of years we grow old and tired. Quite often people get stuck in a rut, and are content with past memories. As we get older, usually we do not feel like taking on fresh challenges. From a practical point of view the body declines, and it becomes increasingly difficult to fulfil our desires and aspirations. Reincarnation enables us to be reborn with new hope and new life. Furthermore, because we do not usually remember our previous incarnations, we can wipe our memory clear of our unfortunate past experience. We may have been a thief in the past, but reincarnation gives us the chance to mend our ways. No one is destined to remain imperfect forever.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Law of Karma.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The law of Karma is a fundamental underlying law of the universe. Basically, the law of karma says; “As you sow so, shall you reap.” The law of karma has been explained and emphasised, in many different religious and spiritual traditions. It is the process of reincarnation, which enables the law of karma to fully operate. In one lifetime you may be born in unfortunate circumstances and be deceived by others. These unfortunate experiences can be rectified in a future incarnation. Similarly, if a person was to profit from the exploitation of others, he may be able to escape the cosmic justice in his current incarnation; but, in future incarnations he would experience the effects of his actions. Nobody can hide forever from their own actions. At the same time, not all karma is inevitable. If we have done wrong things in previous incarnations, it is possible for the effects to be nullified or reduced by God’s grace, or the intervention of a Spiritual Master.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self Realisation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There comes a point in the soul’s evolution, when the entire being; mind, heart, body and soul are aspiring to realise the highest. If we can attain realisation of the Supreme, Transcendental Consciousness, we can escape the cycle of rebirth and death. For example, the Buddha taught that on attaining nirvana it was not necessary for the soul to be continually reborn. However, to attain Self-realisation or nirvana is no easy task. It can take many incarnations to free ourselves from our earthly desires and inherited tendencies. On the one hand, if we aspire most intensely, realisation is possible in this incarnation. But during one lifetime many seekers complete only part of the journey. Reincarnation enables us to make continual progress in the future. Furthermore, to manifest the qualities of the soul can take even more incarnations. As spiritual teacher, Sri Chinmoy says;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It very often happens that realisation can take place in one incarnation, but for manifestation the soul has to come down again and again to earth. Unless and until we reveal and manifest the highest Divinity within us, our game is not over.” [2]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Article By: R.Pettinger&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;References&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] From: Death and Reincarnation by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;[2] Excerpt from Death And Reincarnation by Sri Chinmoy.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/cycle-of-reincarnation-explained.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-976072417806276704</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2007 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-09-08T04:10:28.480-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>srichinmoy</category><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>anger</category><title>Quotes on Anger by Sri Chinmoy</title><description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/blog/inner-peace/10-powerful-ways-to-deal-with-anger/"&gt;Article on dealing with Anger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Quotes by Sri Chinmoy on Anger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"When a man demands anger's quick appearance, God surprises him by His secret disappearance." (1)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"Your monstrous anger&lt;br /&gt;Heralds the fast-approaching hour&lt;br /&gt;Of your life's&lt;br /&gt;Total destruction." (2)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"The animal anger&lt;br /&gt;Eventually surrenders&lt;br /&gt;To the heart-breaking tears and sobs&lt;br /&gt;Of the loving heart." (3)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(1) Excerpt from I Need This Book by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(2) Excerpt from Ten Thousand Flower-Flames, Part 77 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(3) Excerpt from Ten Thousand Flower-Flames, Part 67 by Sri Chinmoy.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/dealing-with-anger.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-1826752742552927441</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2007 07:28:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-05-31T12:07:17.542-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>hate</category><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>love</category><title>Quotes on Love and Hate</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;"Hate is often an obverse form of love.&lt;br /&gt;You hate someone whom you really wish to love but whom you cannot love."&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we hate we actually lose something precious in ourselves. If we bear hatred for others it is like having a stain on our own heart. We may feel it is justified to hate; however, our hatred does not help in anyway. Furthermore, the hate we feel makes us feel miserable, either now or in the future. If we have the capacity to hate we also have the capacity to love. This does not mean we approve of the wrong actions' of others; it just means we maintain an attitude of forgiveness and concentrate on the divine aspect deep inside them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;How To overcome Hate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Hatred can never cease by hatred.&lt;br /&gt;Hatred can only cease by love.&lt;br /&gt;This is an eternal law. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- The Buddha&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is a saying "Hate the crime not the person". If we hate somebody because they have done something wrong, instead we can separate the person from their wrong actions. No matter how bad a person is, there is always the possibility of reformation. It is only ignorance that prevents a person from living according to the aspiration of their soul.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we hate our enemies, what we actually do is to strengthen their bad qualities. By focusing on their bad qualities we magnify and give them greater importance. Sometimes, we hate people even for a minor infraction. Quite often, we hate for for no particular good reason, such as, jealousy or anger. However, when we hate the person, they tend to react in a similar negative way. Our hatred becomes a reason for them to reciprocate the hatred; therefore, it becomes a negative spiral, without an end in sight&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Instead of hatred, if we can maintain an attitude of forgiveness, then we may inspire them to change their ways. It may be that, although, they have some bad qualities they also have good qualities. If they see real forgiveness inside us, it may shame them into mending their ways. When their enemies respond with love rather than hate, it encourages them to do the same.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;No remedy for black hate?&lt;br /&gt;Who says?&lt;br /&gt;Just love&lt;br /&gt;And love more,&lt;br /&gt;That's all.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/"&gt;Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we hate something in another person, quite often, we are actually hating something that is part of our own nature. If we can extend our consciousness we realise our interconnection and oneness with other people. Therefore, rather than concentrating on others' bad qualities, we shall concentrate on our self improvement. To make real self improvement, we need to let go of feelings of hate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To love rather than hate, does not mean we have to approve or tolerate their actions. A mother loves her children, no matter what they do; however, that doesn't mean she approves of their wrong actions. A mother will try to correct her children's wrong actions. However, to change the behaviour of her children she will not adopt an attitude of hate; she knows this will be counter-productive. Instead, she will appeal to their better nature in the hope that some day they will change their behaviour.</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/quotes-on-love-and-hate.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8228764664760154592.post-9035703855271704320</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2007 22:05:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2007-05-28T15:08:17.665-07:00</atom:updated><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>gratitude</category><category domain='http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#'>spiritual qualities</category><title>The Meaning of Gratitude</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;"&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Gratitude is not a mere word; it is not a mere concept. It is the living breath of your real existence on earth.&lt;/span&gt;"&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/"&gt;Sri Chinmoy&lt;/a&gt; [1]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gratitude is a quality which is often underestimated. When we feel and express genuine gratitude we are recognising the good and beautiful aspects of life. Gratitude helps us to appreciate the best in others; it is a very powerful antidote to negativity and depression. To experience gratitude is to make a meaningful connection with our inner self.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gratitude should be unconditional. If we are grateful because somebody has done us a favour, this is good, but it is not the highest form of gratitude. If we only express gratitude when we benefit, it is a limited form of gratitude. Real gratitude is a spontaneous feeling of appreciation and oneness; when we cultivate this kind of gratitude we live in harmony with the underlying nature of the universe.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;How to Cultivate Gratitude.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;The Heart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gratitude is most powerfully an expression and experience of the heart. Our mind is judgemental and critical; the mind can easily find fault. The mind will only be grateful when it perceives a direct benefit. When we live in the heart we can feel gratitude because we have a oneness with others. The nature of the heart is to identify with the good qualities of others. It is in the heart where we can feel unconditional love and gratitude.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;A gratitude-heart&lt;br /&gt;Is to discover on earth&lt;br /&gt;A Heaven-delivered rose.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- Sri Chinmoy [2]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight:bold;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Inner Silence and Meditation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The noise of the mind creates endless thoughts. If we are constantly thinking, we have no chance to rise above the mundane mind. When we maintain an inner silence our divine qualities come to the fore. We feel an inner happiness that is not dependent on outer circumstances. It is when we feel this inner peace and joy that gratitude spontaneously arises.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight:bold;"&gt;Simplicity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gratitude is a divine quality because we are are identifying and appreciating an extended consciousness. Gratitude helps us to be in harmony with our source. Gratitude teachers us that the secret of happiness is not to be found in the success of our ego, or in the complications of the mind. Gratitude means to appreciate and love that which is not part of our limited self.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight:bold;"&gt;Nature.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When we spend time with nature we feel inspired by its beauty and vastness. When we meditate on nature, we feel an aspiration for appreciating the infinite nature of the Universe. Quite often we struggle to comprehend or quantify nature, but when we spend time with nature we feel a growing sense of gratitude.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[1] Excerpt from Sri Chinmoy Answers, Part 1 by Sri Chinmoy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[2] Poems on Gratitude by Sri Chinmoy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Article By: Richard Pettinger, Sri Chinmoy Centre</description><link>http://www.srichinmoybio.co.uk/2007/05/meaning-of-gratitude.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Tejvan Pettinger)</author></item></channel></rss>